<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Australia on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/australia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Australia on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/australia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>changes: easy Git-based version control from R</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/28/ropensci-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/28/ropensci-changes/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;Are you new to version control and always running into trouble with Git?
Or are you a seasoned user, haunted by the traumas of learning Git and reliving them whilst trying to teach it to others?
Yeah, us too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-28-ropensci-changes/monkeys.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Git is a version control tool designed for software development, and it is extraordinarily powerful. It didn’t actually dawn on me quite how amazing Git is until I spent a weekend in Melbourne with a group of Git whizzes using Git to write a package targeted toward Git beginners. Whew, talk about total Git immersion! I was taking part in the 2017 &lt;a href=&#34;https://ozunconf17.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;rOpenSci ozunconf&lt;/a&gt;, in which forty-odd  developers, scientists, researchers, nerds, teachers, starving students, cat ladies, and R users of all descriptions form teams to create new R packages fulfilling some new and useful function. Many of the groups used Git for their collaborative workflows all weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, just like many a programming framework, Git can often be a teensy bit (read: extremely, prohibitively) intimidating, especially for beginners who don&amp;rsquo;t need all of Git&amp;rsquo;s numerous and baffling features.
It’s one of those platforms that makes your life a million times better once you know how to use it, but if you’re trying to teach yourself the basics using the internet, or—heaven forbid—trying to untangle yourself from some Git-branch tangle that you’ve unwittingly become snarled in… (definitely done that one…) well, let’s just say using your knuckles to break a brick wall can sometimes seem preferable.
Just ask the Git whizzes.
They laugh, because they’ve been there, done that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is, doing basic version control in Git only requires a few commands.
After browsing through the available project ideas and settling into teams, a group of eight of us made a list of the commands that we use on a daily basis, and the list came to about a dozen.
We looked up our Git histories and compiled a Git vocabulary, which came out to less than 50 commands, including combination commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/goldingn&#34;&gt;Nick Golding&lt;/a&gt; so shrewdly recognized in the lead up to this year’s unconference, the real obstacle for new Git users is not the syntax, it&amp;rsquo;s actually (a) the scary, scary terminal window and (b) the fact that Git terminology was apparently chosen by randomly opening a verb dictionary and blindly pointing to a spot on the page.
(Ok, I’m exaggerating, but the point is that the terminology is pretty confusing).
We decided to address these two problems by making a package that uses the R console and reimagining the version control vocabulary and workflow for people who are new to version control and only need some of its many features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat ironically, nine people worked for two days on a dozen branches, using Git and GitHub to seamlessly merge our workflows.
It was wonderful to see how so many people’s various talents can be combined to make something that no group members could have done all on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter, &lt;code&gt;changes&lt;/code&gt; ( &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/ozrepro&#34;&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropenscilabs.github.io/changes/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; – made using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hadley/pkgdown&#34;&gt;pkgdown&lt;/a&gt;), our new R package to do version control with a few simple commands.
It uses Git and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/git2r/index.html&#34;&gt;Git2r&lt;/a&gt; under the hood, but new users don’t need to know any Git to begin using version control with &lt;code&gt;changes&lt;/code&gt;.
Best of all, it works seamlessly with regular Git. So if a user thinks they&amp;rsquo;re ready to expand their horizons they can start using git commands via the &lt;a href=&#34;https://GitHub.com/jennybc/Githug&#34;&gt;Githug&lt;/a&gt; package, RStudio&amp;rsquo;s git interface, or on the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an overview of some of the ways we’ve made simple version control easy with &lt;code&gt;changes&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;simple-terminology&#34;&gt;Simple terminology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It uses simple and deliberately un-git-like terminology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You start a new version control project with &lt;code&gt;create_repo()&lt;/code&gt;, which is like &lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt; but it can set up a nice project directory structure for you, automatically ignoring things like output folders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of the steps involved in commiting edits have been compressed into one function: &lt;code&gt;record()&lt;/code&gt;. All files that aren&amp;rsquo;t ignored will be committed, so users don&amp;rsquo;t need to know the difference between tracking, staging and committing files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to set which files to omit from version control with &lt;code&gt;ignore()&lt;/code&gt;, and to change your mind with &lt;code&gt;unignore()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;changes()&lt;/code&gt; lets you know which files have changed since the last record, like a hybrid of &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git diff&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can look back in history with &lt;code&gt;timeline()&lt;/code&gt; (a simplified version of &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;), &lt;code&gt;go_to()&lt;/code&gt; a previous record (like &lt;code&gt;git checkout&lt;/code&gt;), and &lt;code&gt;scrub()&lt;/code&gt; any unwanted changes since the last record (like &lt;code&gt;git reset --hard&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;it-s-linear&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s linear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long discussion, we decided that changes won&amp;rsquo;t provide an interface to Git branches (at least not yet), as the merge conflicts it leads to are one of the scariest things about version control for beginners.
With linear version control, users can can easily &lt;code&gt;go_to()&lt;/code&gt; a past record with a version number, rather than unfamiliar &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Internals-Git-Objects&#34;&gt;SHA&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;. These numbers appear in the a lovely visual representation of their &lt;code&gt;timeline()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;      (1) initial commit
       |  2017-11-18 02:55
       |
      (2) set up project structure
       |  2017-11-18 02:55
       |
      (3) added stuff to readme
          2017-11-18 02:55
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to roll your project back to a previous record, you can &lt;code&gt;retrieve()&lt;/code&gt; it, and changes will simply append that record at the top of your timeline (storing all the later records, just in case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;readable-messages-and-automatic-reminders&#34;&gt;Readable messages and automatic reminders&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of Git&amp;rsquo;s messages and helpfiles are totally cryptic to all but the most hardened computer scientists.
Having been confronted with our fair share of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.git-tower.com/learn/git/faq/detached-head-when-checkout-commit&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;detached HEAD&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s and offers to &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-push&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;update remote refs along with associated objects&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we were keen to make sure all the error messages and helpfiles in changes are as intuitive and understandable as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be hard to get into the swing of recording edits, so changes will give you reminders to encourage you to use &lt;code&gt;record()&lt;/code&gt; regularly. You can change the time interval for reminders, or switch them off, using &lt;code&gt;remind_me()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;coming-soon&#34;&gt;Coming soon&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a lot of progress in two days, but there&amp;rsquo;s plenty more we&amp;rsquo;re planning to add soon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simplified access to GitHub with a &lt;code&gt;sync()&lt;/code&gt; command to automagically handle most uses of &lt;code&gt;git fetch&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git merge&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Git training-wheels mode, so that people who want to move use Git can view the Git commands &lt;code&gt;changes&lt;/code&gt; is using under the hood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added flexibility – we are working on adding functionality to handle simple deviations from the defaults, such as recording changes only to named files, or to all except some excluded files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;d be really keen to hear your suggestions too, so please let us know your ideas via the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/changes/issues&#34;&gt;changes issue tracker&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only recently started using Git and GitHub, and this year’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://ozunconf17.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;rOpenSci ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; was a big eye-opener for me, in several ways.
Beyond finally understanding to power of proper version control, I met a group of wonderful people dedicated to participating in the R community.
Now as it turns out, R users take the word “community” very seriously.
Each and every person I met during the event was open and friendly.
Each person had ideas for attracting new users to R, making it easier to learn, making methods and data more readily available, and creating innovative new functionality.
Even before the workshop began, dozens of ideas for advancement circulated on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/ozunconf17/issues&#34;&gt;GitHub Issues&lt;/a&gt;.
Throughout the conference, it was a pleasure to be a part of the ongoing conversation and dialogue about growing and improving the R community.
That’s right, you can delete any lingering ‘introverted computer geek’ stereotypes you might still be harbouring in a cobwebbed attic of your mind.
In today’s day and age, programming is as much about helping each other, communicating, learning, and networking as it is about solving problems.
And building the community is a group effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R users come from all sorts of backgrounds, but I was gratified to see scientists and researchers well-represented at the unconference.
Gone are the days when I need to feel like the ugly duckling for being the only R user in my biology lab!
If you still find yourself isolated, join the blooming online R users community, or any one of a number of meetups and clubs that are popping up everywhere.
I have dipped my toe in those waters, and boy am I glad I did!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 rOpenSci ozunconf :: Reflections and the realtime Package</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/14/realtime/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/14/realtime/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://ozunconf17.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;rOpenSci ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; was held in Melbourne, bringing together over 45 R enthusiasts from around the country and beyond. As is customary, ideas for projects were discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/ozunconf17/issues&#34;&gt;GitHub Issues&lt;/a&gt; (41 of them by the time the unconf rolled around!) and there was no shortage of enthusiasm, interesting concepts, and varied experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been to a few unconfs now and I treasure the time I get to spend with new people, new ideas, new backgrounds, new approaches, and new insights. That&amp;rsquo;s not to take away from the time I get to spend with people I met at previous unconfs; I&amp;rsquo;ve gained great friendships and started collaborations on side projects with these wonderful people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the call for nominations came around this year it was an easy decision. I don&amp;rsquo;t have employer support to attend these things so I take time off work and pay my own way. This is my networking time, my development time, and my skill-building time. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure what sort of project I&amp;rsquo;d be interested in but I had no doubts something would come up that sounded interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happened, I had been playing around with a bit of code, purely out of interest and hoping to learn how &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htmlwidgets.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;htmlwidgets&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; work. The idea I had was to make a classic graphic equaliser visualisation like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/graphiceq.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;using R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This presents several challenges; how can I get live audio into R, and how fast can I plot the signal? I had doubts about both parts, partly because of the way that R calls tie up the session (&lt;a href=&#34;https://appsilondatascience.com/blog/rstats/2017/11/01/r-promises-hands-on.html&#34;&gt;for now&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt;) and partly because constructing a &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; object is somewhat slow (in terms of raw audio speeds). I&amp;rsquo;d heard about &lt;code&gt;htmlwidgets&lt;/code&gt; and thought there must be a way to leverage that towards my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched for a graphic equaliser javascript library to work with and didn&amp;rsquo;t find much that aligned with what I had in my head. Eventually I stumbled on &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;p5.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and its examples page which has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://p5js.org/examples/sound-frequency-spectrum.html&#34;&gt;audio-input plot with a live demo&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a frequency spectrum, but I figured that&amp;rsquo;s just a bit of binning away from what I need. Running the example there looks like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/p5sound_optimised.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemed to be worth a go. I managed to follow enough of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.htmlwidgets.org/develop_intro.html&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to have the library called from R. I modified the javascript canvas code to look a little more familiar, and the first iteration of &lt;code&gt;geom_realtime()&lt;/code&gt; was born&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3mdiCUbgxi0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; gesture=&#34;media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemed like enough of an idea that I proposed it in the GitHub Issues for the unconf. It got a bit of attention, which was worrying, because I had no idea what to do with this next. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/petehaitch&#34;&gt;Peter Hickey&lt;/a&gt; pointed out that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/seankross&#34;&gt;Sean Kross&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a href=&#34;https://seankross.com/2017/08/11/Beyond-Axes-Simulating-Systems-with-Interactive-Graphics.html&#34;&gt;already wrapped some of the &lt;code&gt;p5.js&lt;/code&gt; calls into R calls&lt;/a&gt; with his &lt;code&gt;p5&lt;/code&gt; package, so this seemed like a great place to start. It&amp;rsquo;s quite a clever way of doing it too; it involves re-writing the &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt; which &lt;code&gt;htmlwidgets&lt;/code&gt; calls on each time you want to do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the unconf and a decent number of people gathered around a little slip of paper with &lt;code&gt;geom_realtime()&lt;/code&gt; written on it. I had to admit to everyone that the &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; aspect of my demo was a sham (it&amp;rsquo;s surprisingly easy to draw a canvas in just the right shade of grey with white gridlines), but people stayed, and we got to work seeing what else we could do with the idea. We came up with some suggestions for input sources, some different plot types we might like to support, and set about trying to understand what Sean&amp;rsquo;s package actually did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it tends to work out, we had a great mix of people with different experience levels in different aspects of the project; some who knew how to make a package, some who knew how to work with &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt;, some who knew how to work with &lt;code&gt;websockets&lt;/code&gt;, some who knew about realtime data sources, and some who knew about nearly none of these things (✋ that would be me). If everyone knew every aspect about how to go about an unconf project I suspect the endeavor would be a bit boring. I love these events because I get to learn so much about so many different topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared my demo script and we deconstructed the pieces. We dug into the inner workings of the &lt;code&gt;p5&lt;/code&gt; package and started determining which parts we could siphon off to meet our own needs. One of the aspects that we wanted to figure out was how to simulate realtime data. This could be useful both for testing, and also in the situation where one might want to &amp;rsquo;re-cast&amp;rsquo; some time-coded data. We were thankful that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kcf-jackson&#34;&gt;Jackson Kwok&lt;/a&gt; had gone deep-dive into &lt;code&gt;websockets&lt;/code&gt; and pretty soon (surprisingly soon, perhaps; within the first day) we had examples of (albeit, constructed) real-time (every 100ms) data streaming from a server and being plotted at-speed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/realtime_runif_optimised.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best of all, running the plot code didn&amp;rsquo;t tie up the session; it uses a listener written into the &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt; so it just waits for input on a particular port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the core goal well underway, people started branching out into aspects they found most interesting. We had some people work on finding and connecting actual data sources, such as the bitcoin exchange rate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/realtime_btc_optimised.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and a live-stream of binary-encoded data from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://qrng.anu.edu.au/index.php&#34;&gt;Australian National University (ANU) Quantum Random Numbers Server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/realtime_bin_optimised.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others formalised the code so that it can be piped into different &amp;lsquo;themes&amp;rsquo;, and retain the &lt;code&gt;p5&lt;/code&gt; structure for adding more components&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/realtime_bw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were still toy examples of course, but they highlight what&amp;rsquo;s possible. They were each constructed using an offshoot of the &lt;code&gt;p5&lt;/code&gt; package whereby the &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt; is re-written to include various features each time the plot is generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another route we took is to use the direct &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt; binding API with factory functions. This had less flexibility in terms of adding modular components, but meant that the &lt;code&gt;javascript&lt;/code&gt; could be modified without worrying about how it needed to interact with &lt;code&gt;p5&lt;/code&gt; so much. This resulted in some outstanding features such as side-scrolling and date-time stamps. We also managed to pipe the data off to another thread for additional processing (in R) before being sent to the plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example we ended up with reads the live-feed of Twitter posts under a given hashtag, computes a sentiment analysis on the words with R, and live-plots the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/auspol.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I was amazed at the progress we made over just two days. Starting from a silly idea/demo, we built a package which can plot realtime data, and can even serve up some data to be plotted. I have no expectations that this will be the way of the future, but it&amp;rsquo;s been a fantastic learning experience for me (and hopefully others too). It&amp;rsquo;s highlighted that there&amp;rsquo;s ways to achieve realtime plots, even if we&amp;rsquo;ve used a library built for drawing rather than one built for plotting per se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s even inspired offshoots in the form of some R packages;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/tRainspotting&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tRainspotting&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which shows realtime data on New South Wales public transport using &lt;code&gt;leaflet&lt;/code&gt; as the canvas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-14-realtime/tRainspotting.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kcf-jackson/jsReact/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;jsReact&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which explores the interaction between R and Javascript&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/kcf-jackson/jsReact/raw/master/inst/example_5.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/kcf-jackson/jsReact/raw/master/inst/example_6.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possibilities are truly astounding. My list of &amp;lsquo;things to learn&amp;rsquo; has grown significantly since the unconf, and projects are still starting up/continuing to develop. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jonocarroll/ggeasy&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggeasy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package isn&amp;rsquo;t related, but it was spawned from another unconf Github Issue idea. Again; ideas and collaborations starting and developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at the unconf, and I can&amp;rsquo;t wait until the next one. My hand will be going up to help out, attend, and help start something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks and congratulations go out to each of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/realtime&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;realtime&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; developers: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/richardbeare&#34;&gt;Richard Beare&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jonocarroll&#34;&gt;Jonathan Carroll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kimnewzealand&#34;&gt;Kim Fitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/softloud&#34;&gt;Charles Gray&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jeffreyhanson&#34;&gt;Jeffrey O Hanson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/holtzy&#34;&gt;Yan Holtz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kcf-jackson&#34;&gt;Jackson Kwok&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MilesMcBain&#34;&gt;Miles McBain&lt;/a&gt; and the entire cohort of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ozunconf17.ropensci.org&#34;&gt;2017 rOpenSci ozunconf attendees&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, my thanks go to the organisers of such a wonderful event; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/njtierney&#34;&gt;Nick Tierney&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/robjhyndman&#34;&gt;Rob Hyndman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dicook&#34;&gt;Di Cook&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MilesMcBain&#34;&gt;Miles McBain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Communities Together at ozunconf, 2017</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/31/ozunconf2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/31/ozunconf2017/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-hex-cookies.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week we organised the 2nd rOpenSci &lt;a href=&#34;http://ozunconf17.ropensci.org&#34;&gt;ozunconference&lt;/a&gt;, the sibling rOpenSci unconference, held in Australia. Last year it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://auunconf.ropensci.org&#34;&gt;held in Brisbane&lt;/a&gt;, this time around, the ozunconf was hosted in Melbourne, from October 26-27, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the ozunconf, we brought together 45 R-software users and developers, scientists, and open data enthusiasts from academia, industry, government, and non-profits. Participants travelled from far and wide, with people coming from 6 cities around Australia, 2 cities in New Zealand, and one city in the USA. Before the ozunconf we discussed and dreamt up projects to work on for a few days, then met up and brought about a bakers dozen of them into reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-womens-data-discuss.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;upskilling-participants&#34;&gt;Upskilling participants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Day 0.5 of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ozunconf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; and an excellent intro to writing packages and using Git from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rdpeng?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@rdpeng&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nj_tierney?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@nj_tierney&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed the post-it note system! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iKTbWkeCA0&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/iKTbWkeCA0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Holly Kirk (@HollyKirk) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HollyKirk/status/923065587915415552?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 25, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Day 0, one day before the ozunconf, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rdpeng&#34;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt; and I ran a half day training session on how to develop R packages and share them on GitHub. The participants picked things up really quickly, and by the end of the session, everyone could make an R package, and push it to GitHub. We also introduced them to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s3JldKoA0zw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34;&gt;the wonders of RMarkdown&lt;/a&gt;. The event then kicked on to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.meetup.com/R-Ladies-Melbourne/events/244102535/&#34;&gt;R-Ladies Melbourne special one year anniversary event&lt;/a&gt;, which featured a great talk and introduction to Random Forests by Elisabeth Vogel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bringing-people-together&#34;&gt;Bringing people together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Biscuit decorating at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ozunconf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; ! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/M8PxOyRUJI&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/M8PxOyRUJI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nikeisha Caruana (@bluebirdi) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/bluebirdi/status/923305923208036352?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 25, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the ozunconf, we discussed various ideas for projects in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/ozunconf17/issues&#34;&gt;the GitHub issues&lt;/a&gt;. Things really started to pick up in the last week and we ended up at 41 issues - almost as many issues as participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-oz-data-discuss.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day one kicked off with decorating some hex cookies, baked by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/visnut&#34;&gt;Di Cook&lt;/a&gt;. This uncovered a fun fact that &lt;a href=&#34;http://stefanbache.dk/&#34;&gt;Stefan Milton Bache&lt;/a&gt; - creator of the beloved pipe operator (&lt;code&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt;) from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tidyverse/magrittr&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;magrittr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package, apparently also created the first #rstats hex sticker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then stuck the various projects that had been discussed throughout the week around the room and participants sticker voted on projects that they were interested in working on. Introductions were made, and quotes like these (from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stephdesilva&#34;&gt;Steph de Silva&lt;/a&gt;) led to entertaining discussions around data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m 50% data hazmat, 50% data grief counselling&amp;quot; best Intro ever at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ozunconf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ozunconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steve Bennett (@stevage1) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stevage1/status/923314625428336641?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 25, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were really lucky to be in the beautiful Monash City Campus, a place that almost seems to have been designed for an unconf, with some classroom style space, as well as plenty of nooks and crannies to sit in, including an outdoor astroturfed garden complete with bean bags and native flora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-earo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The Oz colour palette gang soakin it up outside &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ozunconf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/XiLkhwZwTv&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/XiLkhwZwTv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Miles McBain (@MilesMcBain) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MilesMcBain/status/923682409400250368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 26, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The venue even seemed to reflect our love of hex stickers, providing a nice hex sticker themed carpet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Appropriately shaped carpet pattern for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ozunconf?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ozunconf&lt;/a&gt; venue &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/hex?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#hex&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/QsbVWhCQyb&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/QsbVWhCQyb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Holly Kirk (@HollyKirk) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HollyKirk/status/923420699900997632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 26, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had some great sponsors for this event, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-consortium.org/&#34;&gt;The RConsortium&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://inghaminstitute.org.au/&#34;&gt;The Ingham Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.monash.edu/business&#34;&gt;Monash Business School&lt;/a&gt;. The event was also organised by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nj_tierney&#34;&gt;myself&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/visnut&#34;&gt;Di Cook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/robjhyndman&#34;&gt;Rob Hyndman&lt;/a&gt;, and also &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/milesmcbain&#34;&gt;Miles McBain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-hex-mat.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wrapped up at the end of day 2, giving each projects group three minutes to debrief on their projects, using the unconf style - only the README.md (mostly!). You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropenscilabs.github.io/ozunconf-projects/&#34;&gt;check out all the ozunconf projects here&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to a template from &lt;a href=&#34;http://seankross.com/&#34;&gt;Sean Kross&lt;/a&gt;. Soon we will publish a series of short posts covering some of these great fun projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick taster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/realtime&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;realtime&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Realtime streamingplots built on the p5.js library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/ozrepro&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A simplified version control interface to git, from within R.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/icon&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;icon&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Easily access and insert web icons into HTML and PDF documents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/ochRe&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ochRe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Provide Australia-themed Colour Palettes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll share a quick summary of all of the projects over the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-your-story&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Your Story?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StephdeSilva/status/923875737102200832&#34;&gt;Some key #ozunconf lessons from Steph de Silva&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The opportunity to try but not succeed is a luxury to be savoured&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mistakes make you a better programmer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best thing about R isn&amp;rsquo;t the language, it&amp;rsquo;s the number of people around who want to help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your skills are valuable, so your productivity is too. Investing in the tools that maximise it is worthwhile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git really is out to get you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few people have already written about their unconf17 experience. Have you? Share the link in the comments below and we&amp;rsquo;ll add it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;projects-posts&#34;&gt;Projects posts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.healthintersections.com.au/?p=2740&#34;&gt;FHIR and R: &lt;code&gt;ronfhir&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.healthintersections.com.au/&#34;&gt;Grahame Grieve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/14/realtime/&#34;&gt;2017 rOpenSci ozunconf :: Reflections and the &lt;code&gt;realtime&lt;/code&gt; Package&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://jcarroll.com.au/&#34;&gt;Jonathan Carroll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/21/ochre/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ochRe&lt;/code&gt; - Australia themed colour palettes&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HollyKirk&#34;&gt;Holly Kirk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/visnut&#34;&gt;Di Cook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alicia-a&#34;&gt;Alicia Allan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ross_gayler&#34;&gt;Ross Gayler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rdpeng&#34;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ellesaber&#34;&gt;Elle Saber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;community-posts&#34;&gt;Community posts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://simplystatistics.org/2017/10/30/how-do-you-convince-others-to-use-r/&#34;&gt;How do you convince others to use R?&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~rpeng/&#34;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rex-analytics.com/failure-is-an-option/&#34;&gt;Failure Is An Option&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StephdeSilva&#34;&gt;Steph da Silva&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introducing-people-to-the-ropensci-community&#34;&gt;Introducing people to the rOpenSci community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rOpenSci has had a profound impact on me and my work. At the end of 2015 I got in touch with them to discuss arranging an unconference in Australia, and they welcomed me and my friends. Today, I am proud to be welcoming those from the ozunconf to this big, kind, wonderful community, and say, as Shannon Ellis summed up: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/06/23/community/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hey! You there! You are welcome here&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was also really great to have a diverse group of participants at the ozunconf, and in particular, that 40% of participants were women or other underrepresented genders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;starts-not-ends&#34;&gt;Starts, not ends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve realised in my involvement with organising and attending these events is that when the unconf ends, it feels a bit sad, sure, to say goodbye to the environment, the community, the friends, and the projects. At the last unconf in LA, we were sending out a stream of tweets, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nj_tierney/status/868572134548713472&#34;&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MilesMcBain/status/868590677843599360&#34;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/868605633435533312&#34;&gt;until&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MilesMcBain/status/869044724086185985&#34;&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dataandme/status/869664700606406656&#34;&gt;over&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. But, in reflection, standing back, taking it all in, the unconference doesn&amp;rsquo;t really end - it just starts. It starts many new things - projects, ideas, collaborations, and friendships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ozunconf comes to an end. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://njtierney.updog.co/img/ozunconf-group-photo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Australia Unconference</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/06/16/au-unconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/06/16/au-unconf/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;On April 21st and 22nd of 2016, we had 40 members of the R community gather in Brisbane, Australia, with the goal of reproducing the rOpensci Unconference events that have been running with great success in San Francisco since 2014. Like every event organisers ever, we went through the usual crisis: Where will it be? Will anyone actually show up? Is the problem space over venue, date, attendees, catering, sponsors convex? It it even possible to organise an event by only uttering TRUE statements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It ain&amp;rsquo;t easy being green. The fact that back in December 2015 Karthik Ram agreed to a proposal to essentially franchise the rOpensci unconference to a few junior researchers he’d never heard of, from a place a long way away, with enthusiasm for rOpensci’s ideals as their only redeeming qualities, still astounds us. More than that, it speaks volumes about the accessibility of this community to anyone that believes in what it stands for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So sustained by coaching from Karthik, encouragement from local R luminaries, and generous support from sponsors who jumped right on the idea, we pulled together together an event that captured the spirit of those that have come before and got the community interested. The final event attracted a stellar cohort of participants from post grad students, post-docs and tenured professors, to industry statisticians and government data scientists. Attendees travelled from across Australia, New Zealand and even Singapore. Together we represented a diversity of organisations including Queensland University of Technology, University of Melbourne, Monash University, University of Iowa, University of Auckland, Microsoft, University of Adelaide, CSIRO, ACEMS, AACo, QLD Museum, QLD government and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard not to gush about. It&amp;rsquo;s the most validating feeling to see the community rally around this idea of getting together in the name of open source, open science, and solving each other&amp;rsquo;s problems. It was such a privilege to be amongst this group of incredibly intelligent and giving people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot below shows the breakdown of the attendees in terms of gender and profession, both areas that we hope to improve in regards to diversity in 2017. We particularly hope to attract more women from the grad student cohort, as well as a wider representation from across industry and government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/assets/blog-images/auunconf16/au_unconf_demog.png&#34; alt=&#34;Attendee Demographics&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much to our delight, it turns out that collecting a bunch of smart, passionate people and freeing them from distractions for 2 days works at least as spectacularly down-under as it has in the United States. And while the outcomes of this event are far greater than a set of packages, we are proud to introduce you to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/eechidna&#34;&gt;Eechidna&lt;/a&gt; (Now on CRAN!) is a package for easily creating visual mashups of Australian electoral and demographic data. Arriving just in time for the lead up to the Australian election (July 2). In the next few days we will launch a visualisation competition around the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/saundersk1/auunconf16&#34;&gt;A collection of vignettes&lt;/a&gt; for pulling Australian weather data into R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/swish-climate-impact-assessment/awaptools&#34;&gt;Awaptools&lt;/a&gt;, a helpful colleciton of methods for downloading, and unzipping Australian weather grids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/leafier&#34;&gt;Leafier&lt;/a&gt;, is an impressive proof of concept for enhancing the performance of large spatial datasets in leaflet. The presentation for this one induced one of those magical ‘collective intake of breath moments’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropenscilabs/snowball&#34;&gt;Snowball&lt;/a&gt;, a framework for adminstering AWS clusters and scheduling cluster jobs from within R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Brisbane-Users-of-R-Group-BURGr/&#34;&gt;BURGr&lt;/a&gt;, the Brisbane Users of R Group was born out of the conference and will be having its first meetup this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback from participants has been positive. The unconference format was a real hit and there has been a lot of encouragement to keep 2017 similarly small, with a similar format. We agree! We also see the merits of a ‘primer’ session on open source/open science tools before the main event, so that everyone can start off on similar footing. The voting process for selecting issues was also identified as needing tweaking and we’re going to address that too. This is a great thing about the unconference format: since everyone helps create the experience, everyone is invested and wants to see it thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what you’ve been reading about and want to be involved in 2017, &lt;a href=&#34;http://auunconf.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;you can register your interest on our site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude this post we would like to give a heartfelt thanks to our sponsors. These guys get it! Thank you to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-au&#34;&gt;Microsoft Innovation Centre, Brisbane&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://acems.org.au/&#34;&gt;ACEMS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aaco.com.au/&#34;&gt;AACo&lt;/a&gt; for the support to make the first rOpenSci Unconference happen in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/assets/blog-images/auunconf16/au_hackthon1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lounge hacking&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/assets/blog-images/auunconf16/au_hackthon2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Window hacking&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/assets/blog-images/auunconf16/au_hackthon3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Main Room hacking&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/assets/blog-images/auunconf16/au_organizers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Miles, Jonathan, Jessie, Nick&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
