<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sustainability on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/sustainability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sustainability on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/sustainability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Governance, Engagement, and Resistance in the Open Science Movement: A Comparative Study</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/06/sholler-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/06/sholler-plan/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;A growing community of scientists from a variety of disciplines is moving the norms of scientific research toward open practices. Supporters of open science hope to increase the quality and efficiency of research by enabling the widespread sharing of datasets, research software source code, publications, and other processes and products of research. The speed at which the open science community seems to be growing mirrors the rapid development of technological capabilities, including robust open source scientific software, new services for data sharing and publication, and novel data science techniques for working with massive datasets. Organizations like rOpenSci harness such capabilities and deploy various combinations of these research tools, or what I refer to here as open science infrastructures, to facilitate open science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As studies of other digital infrastructures have pointed out, developing and deploying the technological capabilities that support innovative work within a community of practitioners constitutes just one part of making innovation happen. As quickly as the technical solutions to improving scientific research may be developing, a host of organizational and social issues are lagging behind and hampering the open science community’s ability to inscribe open practices in the culture of scientific research. Remedying organizational and social issues requires paying attention to open science infrastructures’ human components, such as designers, administrators, and users, as well as the policies, practices, and organizational structures that contribute to the smooth functioning of these systems.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These elements of infrastructure development have, in the past, proven to be equal to or more important than technical capabilities in determining the trajectory the infrastructure takes (e.g., whether it “succeeds” or “fails”).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a postdoc with rOpenSci, I have begun a qualitative, ethnographic project to explore the organizational and social processes involved in making open science the norm in two disciplines: astronomy and ecology. I focus on these two disciplines to narrow, isolate, and compare the set of contextual factors (e.g., disciplinary histories, research norms, and the like) that might influence perceptions of open science. Specifically, I aim to answer the following research questions (RQ):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ1a: What are the primary motivations of scientists who actively engage with open science infrastructures?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ1b: What are the factors that influence resistance to open science among some scientists?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ2: What strategies do open science infrastructure leaders use to encourage participation, govern contributions, and overcome resistance to open science infrastructure use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. To what extent do governance strategies balance standardization and flexibility, centralization and decentralization, and voluntary and mandatory contributions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. By what mechanisms are open science policies and practices enforced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c. What are the commonalities and differences in the rationale behind choices of governance strategies?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I describe how I am systematically investigating these questions in two parts. In Part 1, I am identifying the issues raised by scientists who engage with or resist the open science movement. In Part 2, I am studying the governance strategies open science leaders and decision-makers use to elicit engagement with open science infrastructures in these disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-1-engagement-with-and-resistance-to-open-science&#34;&gt;Part 1: Engagement with and Resistance to Open Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am firmly rooted in a research tradition which emphasizes that studying the uptake of a new technology or technological approach, no matter the type of work or profession, begins with capturing how the people charged with changing their activities respond to the change “on the ground.” In this vein, Part 1 of the study aims to lend empirical support or opposition to arguments for and against open science that are commonly found in opinion pieces, on social media, and in organizational mission statements. A holistic reading of such documents reveals several commonalities in the positions for and against open science. Supporters of open science often cite increased transparency, reproducibility, and collaboration as the overwhelming benefits of making scientific research processes and products openly available. Detractors highlight concerns over “scooping,” ownership, and the time costs of curating and publishing code and data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am seeking to verify and test these claims by interviewing and surveying astronomers and ecologists or, more broadly, earth and environmental scientists who fall on various parts of the open science engagement-to-resistance spectrum. I am conducting interviews using a semi-structured interview protocol&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; across all interviewees. I will then use a qualitative data analysis approach based on the grounded theory method&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to extract themes from the responses, focusing on the factors that promote engagement (e.g., making data available, spending time developing research software, or making publications openly accessible) or resistance (e.g., unwillingness to share code used in a study or protecting access to research data). Similar questions will be asked at scale via a survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with themes from the responses, I will clarify and refine the claims often made in the public sphere about the benefits and drawbacks of open science. I hope to develop this part of the study into actionable recommendations for promoting open science, governing contributions to open science repositories, and addressing the concerns of scientists who are hesitant about engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-2-focusing-on-governance&#34;&gt;Part 2: Focusing on Governance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with interviews and surveys of scientists on the ground, it is difficult to systematically trace and analyze the totality of social and political processes that support open science infrastructure development because the processes occur across geographic, disciplinary, and other boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as others have pointed out,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the organizational and social elements of digital infrastructure development often become visible and amenable to study through infrastructure governance. Governance refers to the combination of “executive and management roles, program oversight functions organized into structures, and policies that define management principles and decision making.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Effective governance provides projects with the direction and oversight necessary to achieve desired outcomes of infrastructure development while allowing room for creativity and innovation.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Studying a project’s governance surfaces the negotiation processes that occur among stakeholders—users, managers, organizations, policymakers, and the like—throughout the development process. Outcomes include agreements about the types of technologies used, standards defining the best practices for technology use, and other policies to ensure that a robust, sustainable infrastructure evolves.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the scientific research community’s increasing reliance on open science infrastructures, few studies compare different infrastructure governance strategies&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and even fewer develop new or revised strategies for governing infrastructure development and use.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The primary goal of this part of the project is to address this gap in our understanding of the governance strategies used to create, maintain, and grow open science infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am administering this part of the study by conducting in-depth, semi-structured interviews with leaders of various open science infrastructure projects supporting work in astronomy and ecology. I define “leaders” in this context as individuals or small groups of individuals who make decisions about the management of open science infrastructures and their component parts. This set of leaders includes founders and administrators of widely-used scientific software packages and collections of packages, of open data repositories, of open access publication and preprint services, and various combinations of open science tools. Furthermore, I intend to interview the leaders of organizations with which the open science community interacts—top publication editors, for example—to gauge how open science practices and processes are being governed outside of active open science organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conduct qualitative coding as described above to develop themes from the responses of open science leaders. I will then ground these themes in the literature on digital infrastructure governance—which emphasizes gradual, decentralized, and voluntary development—and look for avenues to improve governance strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the interview and survey methods, I am actively observing and retaining primary documents from the ongoing discourse around open science in popular scientific communication publications (e.g., &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;), conferences and meetings (e.g., OpenCon and discipline-specific hackweeks), and in the popular media/social media (e.g., &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt; and Twitter threads).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;preliminary-themes&#34;&gt;Preliminary Themes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I entered this project with a very basic understanding of how open science “works”—the technical and social mechanisms by which scientists make processes and outputs publicly available. In learning about the open science movement, in general and in particular instantiations, I’ve begun to see the intricacies involved in efforts to change scientific research and its modes of communication: research data publication, citation, and access; journal publication availability; and research software development and software citation standards. Within the community trying to sustain these changes are participants and leaders who are facing and tackling several important issues head-on. I list some of the most common engagement, resistance, and governance challenges appearing in interview and observation transcripts below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;participation-challenges&#34;&gt;Participation challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overcoming the fear of sharing code and data, specifically the fear of sharing “messy” code and the fear of being shamed for research errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defending the time and financial costs of participation in open science—particularly open source software development—to supervisors, collaborators, or tenure and promotion panels who are not engaged with open science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding time to make code and data usable for others (e.g., through good documentation or complete metadata) and, subsequently, finding a home where code and data can easily be searched and found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;governance-challenges&#34;&gt;Governance challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigating the issue of convincing researchers that software development and data publication/archiving “count” as research products, even though existing funding, publication, and tenure and promotion models may not yet value those contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing guidelines and processes for conducting peer review on research publication, software, and data contributions, especially the tensions involved in “open review.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deciding whose responsibility it is to enforce code and data publication standards or policies, both within open science organizations and in traditional outlets like academic journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The points raised in this post and the questions guiding my project might seem like discussions you’ve had too many times over coffee during a hackathon break or over beers after a conference session. If so, I’d love to hear from you, even if you are not an astronomer, an ecologist, or an active leader of an open science infrastructure (dsholler at berkeley dot edu). I am always looking for new ideas, both confirming and disconfirming, to refine my approach to this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- references --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Braa, J., Hanseth, O., Heywood, A., Mohammed, W., Shaw, V. 2007. Developing health information systems in developing countries: The flexible standards strategy. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 31(2), 381-402. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148796&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148796&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Tilson, D., Lyytinen, K., Sørensen, C. 2010 Digital infrastructures: The missing IS research agenda. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 21(4), 748-759. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1100.0318&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1100.0318&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Borgman, C. L. 2010. &lt;i&gt;Scholarship in the digital age: Information, infrastructure, and the Internet.&lt;/i&gt; MIT Press, Cambridge, MA. ISBN: 9780262250863
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Vaast, E., Walsham, G. 2009. Trans-situated learning: Supporting a network of practice with an information infrastructure. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 20(4), 547-564. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1080.0228&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1080.0228&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Spradley, J. P. (2016). &lt;i&gt;The ethnographic interview&lt;/i&gt;. Longegrove, IL: Waveland Press. ISBN: 0030444969
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Corbin, J., Strauss, A.,  1990. Grounded theory research: Procedures, canons, and evaluative criteria. &lt;i&gt;Qualitative Sociology&lt;/i&gt;, 13(1), 3-21. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00988593&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00988593&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Barrett, M., Davidson, E., Prabhu, J., Vargo, S. L. 2015. Service innovation in the digital age: Key contributions and future directions. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 39(1) 135-154. DOI: 10.25300/MISQ/2015/39:1.03
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Hanford, M. 2005. Defining program governance and structure. &lt;i&gt;IBM developerWorks&lt;/i&gt;. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/rational/library/apr05/hanford/&#34;&gt;https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/rational/library/apr05/hanford/&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Star, S. L., Ruhleder, K. 1996. Steps toward an ecology of infrastructure: Design and access for large information spaces. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 7(1), 111-134. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.7.1.111&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.7.1.111&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Edwards, P. N., Jackson, S. J., Bowker, G. C., Knobel, C. P. 2007. &lt;i&gt;Understanding infrastructure: Dynamics, tensions, and design. Final report for Workshop on History and Theory of Infrastructure: Lessons for New Scientific Cyberinfrastructures&lt;/i&gt;. NSF Report. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/49353&#34;&gt;https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/49353&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Hanseth, O., Jacucci, E., Grisot, M., Aanestad, M. 2006. Reflexive standardization: Side effects and complexity in standard making. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 30(1), 563-581. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148773&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148773&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Hanseth, O., &amp;amp; Lyytinen, K. (2010). Design theory for dynamic complexity in information infrastructures: the case of building internet. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Information Technology&lt;/i&gt;, 25(1), 1-19.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to sustainability models for research software projects</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/01/09/sustaining-research-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/01/09/sustaining-research-projects/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;A research project often starts with a bright idea and an initial commitment of volunteer time, or perhaps,
a fixed term grant. But what happens after that initial activity? How can the project continue to
sustain itself? (We define sustainability as the capacity to endure. Software is sustainable if it
will continue to be available in the future, on new platforms, and meeting new needs.
[This is from slide 23 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/danielskatz/scientific-software-challenges-and-community-responses&#34;&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/danielskatz/scientific-software-challenges-and-community-responses&lt;/a&gt;,
though it may have been taken from somewhere else earlier - if you know where, let me know.])&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-guide-to-sustainability-models-for-research-software-projects&#34;&gt;A guide to sustainability models for research software projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on work from Nadia Eghbal (@nayafia on GitHub), who studied how people fund their work on open source projects
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nayafia/lemonade-stand&#34;&gt;https://github.com/nayafia/lemonade-stand&lt;/a&gt;), I wanted to understand how
the projects themselves are sustained. Nadia thought this was out of scope for her document
(see &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nayafia/lemonade-stand/issues/1&#34;&gt;https://github.com/nayafia/lemonade-stand/issues/1&lt;/a&gt;), so I forked her work and created&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects&#34;&gt;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intent has been to list how projects support themselves over time. Each funding category
ideally links to several real examples, and when possible, to a useful article or page instead of just a homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The categories are not mutually exclusive. For example, a project might have a foundation but also use
crowdfunding to raise money. Another project might provide services and also have a donation button. Etc.
The purpose of this guide is to provide an exhaustive list of all the ways a project can survive, so that
your project can figure out what works best for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;possible-next-steps&#34;&gt;Possible next steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Neil Chue Hong (@npch on GitHub) suggests (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects/issues/3&#34;&gt;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects/issues/3&lt;/a&gt;), it&amp;rsquo;s likely that some models
are better suited for particular stages of a project or for particularly types of projects.  It would be useful to
examine the current examples to see what we can learn from them.  We could also learn from a much wider variety of
projects, perhaps by a survey where we ask what models they have successfully used (and unsuccessfully tried), along
with questions about what phases the projects has been in, and &amp;ldquo;demographic&amp;rdquo; information about the project (e.g.,
size, research domain, general purpose vs specific, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;call-for-contributions&#34;&gt;Call for contributions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have examples to add or other changes to suggest to the current document, please do so via pull requests&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have suggestions for how to start addressing the suitability of each model for a project or phase of a project,
please contribute to the existing issue (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects/issues/3&#34;&gt;https://github.com/danielskatz/sustaining-research-projects/issues/3&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, any other comments and suggestions are also welcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software sustainability research with rOpenSci</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/05/25/software-sustanability-ropensci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/05/25/software-sustanability-ropensci/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to announce that I’ve started a project with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org&#34;&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt;
under &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2015/11/19/helmsley-trust-funding/&#34;&gt;their recent award from the Helmsley Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with rOpenSci will focus on sustainability of the project itself.  Sustainability can be defined as having the
resources to do the necessary work to continue and grow rOpenSci.  This is one of the most difficult challenges for
rOpenSci and for many other research software projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rOpenSci has a very broad and very ambitious goal, as stated on their web site, &amp;ldquo;Transforming science through open data.&amp;rdquo;
In practice, the work being done by rOpenSci is &amp;ldquo;creating packages that allow access to data repositories through the
R statistical programming environment&amp;rdquo; with tools that “not only facilitate drawing data into an environment where it
can readily be manipulated, but also one in which those analyses and methods can be easily shared, replicated, and
extended by other researchers.”
An interesting question is how much rOpenSci will choose to move beyond R to meet its goal, which I would encourage as
much as possible.  I actually might rephrase the goal as &amp;ldquo;Transforming science through open data and open software&amp;rdquo;
better matching what is now happening in the project while not calling out R, since I would prefer to try to affect
the non-R science community as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sustainability-resources-work&#34;&gt;Sustainability = Resources &amp;gt; Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of sustainability models that have worked for other open source projects
to bring in the resources needed to do the work,
such as institutional support, diversified grants, membership fees, donations and gifts, fees for services, volunteers,
etc.  With the rOpenSci team, I will test elements of these models for rOpenSci.  As part of this, I will also work
with the rOpenSci leadership team to identify new funding opportunities for rOpenSci from public and private funding
organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will discuss and document how other projects have increased their scale of impact without an equivalent
increase in their staff, and how these models could work for rOpenSci.  I and the rOpenSci team will then test elements
of one or more of these activities.  I will also seek to find new partnership opportunities for rOpenSci with academic,
government, and private organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainability is a key challenge for many academic open source projects, as I saw when I was leading NSF&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=504817&#34;&gt;SI2 program&lt;/a&gt;.  One of the review criteria for proposals
to this program was to describe the proposed sustainability plan.  Few proposers gave fully convincing plans,
and the most common was probably to have a diverse set of funding sources.  Additionally, many projects
decided that they would leave sustainability until near the end of the project.  While we don&amp;rsquo;t know what
will lead to sustainability for academic open source software,
it seems clear that waiting to address it is not likely to make the effort
more successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can solve this for rOpenSci, or even just make progress and
provide guidance for other projects about what might work and what
probably won&amp;rsquo;t, this will be a significant contribution.
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk/&#34;&gt;WSSSPE&lt;/a&gt; events will be a way to bring together
some of the academic open source community to understand how our lessons apply to other
projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;promoting-open-source&#34;&gt;Promoting Open Source&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of this work with rOpenSci, which overlaps some of my other work, involves ideas about how to develop the
overall scientific software community.
Working with the rOpenSci project and the wider scientific software community, I will examine incentives,
citation/credit models, and metrics, including understanding contributions of people in teams; funding models;
multi-disciplinary science; career paths for software developers and scientists who also develop some software;
software engineering; software communities and sociology; training and education; software dissemination, publication,
and peer review; catalogs, search, and review; portability; and reproducibility.  At least some of this will be done
under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk/&#34;&gt;WSSSPE&lt;/a&gt; umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also work with rOpenSci to attempt to promote and encourage software
metrics. A number of projects, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/njsmith/sempervirens&#34;&gt;sempervirens&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://depsy.org&#34;&gt;Depsy&lt;/a&gt;, have begun to focus on particular parts of the problem space, but more general work and
tools are needed, in particular to impact those outside of just the R and python communities.  There’s also some
related work underway at NCSA and RENCI (that came out of WSSSPE3) to survey a set of developers on what impact
metrics they find useful, and I think the results of the survey will also help this overall community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-culture-around-open-source-needs-improvement&#34;&gt;The Culture around Open Source Needs Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to try to change our cultural understanding around the idea of open
source software.  The fact that open source software is commonly viewed as free software is a problem, since to many
people, free means of no value.  In particular, I believe we need to try to get to the point where companies that
make heavy use of open source software feel that they have an obligation to support either the software or its
developers in some way.  This is part of the larger sustainability discussion, since this is the way that open
source projects can gain more resources and reduce the amount of work that they have to do internally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts, comments, or suggestions are welcome. This is also cross-posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://danielskatzblog.wordpress.com/2016/05/25/software-sustainability-research-with-ropensci/&#34;&gt;Dan&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
