<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ropensci Team on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/ropensci-team/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ropensci Team on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/ropensci-team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Value of Welcome, part 2: How to prepare 40 new community members for an unconference</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/12/01/unconf-welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/12/01/unconf-welcome/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;I’ve raved about the value of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/07/18/value-of-welcome/&#34;&gt;extending a personalized welcome&lt;/a&gt; to new community members and I recently shared &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/17/unconf-sixtips&#34;&gt;six tips for running a successful hackathon-flavoured unconference&lt;/a&gt;. Building on these, I’d like to share the specific approach and (free!) tools I used to help prepare new rOpenSci community members to be productive at our &lt;a href=&#34;http://unconf17.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;unconference&lt;/a&gt;. My approach was inspired directly by my &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/introducing-the-2017-community-engagement-fellows/&#34;&gt;AAAS Community Engagement Fellowship Program&lt;/a&gt; (AAAS-CEFP) training. Specifically, 1) one mentor said that the most successful conference they ever ran involved having one-to-one meetings with all participants prior to the event, and 2) prior to our in-person AAAS-CEFP training, we completed an intake questionnaire that forced us to consider things like “what do you hope to get out of this” and “what do you hope to contribute”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A challenge of this year’s unconference was the fact that we were inviting 70 people to participate. As a rule, one third of the crowd will have participated in one of our previous unconferences and two-thirds would be first-time participants. With only two days together, these people need to quickly self-sort into project groups and get working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I sent this email to 45 first-time participants:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-12-01-unconf-welcome/pre-unconf-email.png&#34; alt=&#34;pre-unconf-email&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arranging meetings is one of my least favorite activities, but the free &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendly.com/&#34;&gt;Calendly tool&lt;/a&gt; made this process relatively painless. When a person clicks on the calendar link in the email above, it reveals only times that I am available in my Google Calendar, the time slot they choose shows up in my calendar, and I receive a confirmation email indicating who booked a meeting with me. In my busiest week, I had 19 meetings, but that meant the bulk of them were done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the meeting time most effective I followed AAAS-CEFP program director &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LouWoodley&#34;&gt;Lou Woodley’s&lt;/a&gt; model for onboarding our AAAS CEFP cohort by sending a set of questions to be answered in advance. I took the model to the next level by creating a free &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.ca/forms/about/&#34;&gt;Google Form&lt;/a&gt; questionnaire so that all answers were automatically collected and could be viewed per individual or collectively, and automatically exported to a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-12-01-unconf-welcome/pre-unconf-google-form.png&#34; alt=&#34;pre-unconf-google-form&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions included:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;List three things you hope to get from the unconference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples: &lt;em&gt;connect with people working in a similar domain&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;learn about best practices in data science with R&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;develop a new package that does X&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;List three things you hope to contribute to the unconference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples: &lt;em&gt;expertise or experience in X&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mentoring skills&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;write all the docs!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you had any previous interactions with the rOpenSci community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples: &lt;em&gt;I read the rOpenSci blog&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;I submitted software for rOpenSci open peer review&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you have any concerns about your readiness to participate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples: &lt;em&gt;I’ve never developed an R package&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;How do I decide what project to work on?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would you be interested in writing a blog post about your unconference project or your unconference experience?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you  have a preferred working style or anything you would like to let us know about how you work best?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples: &lt;em&gt;I’m an introvert who likes to take my lunch alone sometimes to recover from group activities – it doesn’t mean I’m not having fun.&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I know I have a tendency to dominate in group discussions – it’s totally fine to ask me to step back and let others contribute. I won’t be offended.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions encouraged participants to reflect in advance. The example answer snippets we provided gave them ideas from which to seed their answers and in some cases gave them permission to show some vulnerability. Individual’s answers gave me cues for things to address in our chat and freed both of us to spend our time talking about the most important issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers to the question “List three things you hope to get from the unconf” were so heartening:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-12-01-unconf-welcome/unconf-three-things.png&#34; alt=&#34;unconf-three-things&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beautiful, but in a different way, were answers to the question, “Do you have any concerns about your readiness to participate?”. People expressed real concerns about impostor syndrome, their perceived ability to contribute &amp;ldquo;as much or as well&amp;rdquo; as others, and feeling &amp;ldquo;outclassed by all the geniuses present&amp;rdquo;. These responses prompted me to reassure people that they were 100% qualified to participate, and opened an opportunity to listen to and address specific concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conduct the pre-unconference chats, I used video conferencing via &lt;a href=&#34;https://appear.in/&#34;&gt;appear.in&lt;/a&gt;, a free, browser-based application that does not require plugins or user accounts. Rather than being exhausted from these calls, I felt energized and optimistic and I experienced many direct positive outcomes. These conversations enabled me to prime people to connect on day-one of the unconference with others with similar interests or from related work sectors. Frequently, I noticed that immediately after our conversation, first-time participants would join the online discussion of existing project ideas, or they themselves proposed new ideas. My conversations with two first-time participants led directly to their proposing community-focussed projects - a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/unconf17/issues/63&#34;&gt;group discussion&lt;/a&gt; and a new &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/unconf17/issues/64&#34;&gt;blog series of interviews&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexpected benefit was that questions people asked me during the video chats led to actions I could take to improve the unconference. For example, when someone wanted to know what previous participants wished they knew beforehand, I asked for and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rOpenSci/status/855531572081991680&#34;&gt;shared example resources&lt;/a&gt;. One wise person asked me what my plan was for having project teams report out at the end of the unconference and this led directly to a streamlined plan (See &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2017-11-17-unconf-sixtips&#34;&gt;Six tips for running a successful unconference&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to AAAS CEFP training for giving me the confidence to try this community experiment! Arranging and carrying out these pre-unconference questionnaires and video chats took a big investment of my time and energy and yet, I consider this effort to be one of the biggest contributors to participants’ satisfaction with the unconference. Will 100% do this again!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Six tips for running a successful unconference</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/17/unconf-sixtips/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/11/17/unconf-sixtips/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ropensci.org/img/blog-images/2017-11-17-unconf-sixtips/ropensci-unconf17-community-nistara-randawa.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Attendees at the May 2017 rOpenSci unconference. Photo credit: Nistara Randhawa&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Attendees at the May 2017 rOpenSci unconference. Photo credit: Nistara Randhawa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2017, I helped run a wildly successful “unconference” that had a huge positive impact on the community I serve. rOpenSci is a non-profit initiative enabling open and reproducible research by creating technical infrastructure in the form of staff- and community-contributed software tools in the R programming language that lower barriers to working with scientific data sources on the web, and creating social infrastructure through a welcoming and diverse community of software users and developers. Our 4th annual unconference brought together 70 people to hack on projects they dreamed up and to give them opportunities to meet and work together in person. One third of the participants had attended before, and two thirds were first-timers, selected from an open call for applications. We paid all costs up front for anyone who requested this in order to lower barriers to participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called an “unconference” because there is no schedule set before the event – participants discuss project ideas online in advance and projects are selected by participant-voting at the start. I’m sharing some tips here on how to do this well for this particular flavour of unconference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-have-a-code-of-conduct&#34;&gt;1. Have a code of conduct&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/blog/2016/12/21/commcallv12-review-coc&#34;&gt;code of conduct&lt;/a&gt; that the organizers promote in the welcome goes a long way to creating a welcoming and safe environment and preventing violations in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-host-online-discussion-of-project-ideas-before-the-unconference&#34;&gt;2. Host online discussion of project ideas before the unconference&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our unconference centered on teams working on programming projects, rather than discussions, so prior to the unconference, we asked all participants to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/unconf17/issues/&#34;&gt;suggest project ideas&lt;/a&gt; using an open online system, called GitHub, that allows everyone to see and comment on ideas or just share enthusiastic emoji to show support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-have-a-pre-unconference-video-chat-with-first-time-participants&#34;&gt;3. Have a pre-unconference video-chat with first-time participants&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our AAAS CEFP training emphasizes the importance of extending a personalized welcome to community members, so I was inspired to make the bold move of talking with more than 40 first-time participants prior to the unconference. I asked each person to complete a short questionnaire to get them to consider the roles they anticipated playing prior to our chat. Frequently, within an hour of a video-chat, without prompting, I would see the person post a new project idea or share their thoughts about someone else’s. Other times, our conversation gave the person an opportunity to say “this idea maybe isn’t relevant but…” and I would help them talk through it, inevitably leading to “oh my gosh this is such a cool idea”. I got a huge return on my investment. People’s questions like “how do you plan to have 20 different projects present their work?” led to better planning on my part. Specific ideas for improvements came from me responding with “well…how would YOU do it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the emails, slack channel, issues on GitHub, and personal video chats, I felt completely at ease going into the unconf (where I knew next to no one!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-rOpenSci unconf17 participant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-run-an-effective-ice-breaker&#34;&gt;4. Run an effective ice breaker&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I adapted the “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facinghistory.org/resource-library/teaching-strategies/barometer-taking-stand-controversial-issues&#34;&gt;Human Barometer&lt;/a&gt;” ice breaker to enable 70 people to share opinions across all perceived levels of who a participant is and introduce themselves to the entire group within a 1 hour period. Success depended on creating questions that were relevant to the unconference crowd, and on visually keeping track of who had spoken up in order to call on those who had not. Ice breakers and the rOpenSci version of the Human Barometer will be the subject of a future CEFP blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-have-a-plan-to-capture-content&#34;&gt;5. Have a plan to capture content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much work and money go into running a great unconference, you can’t afford to do it without a plan to capture and disseminate stories about the people and the products. Harness the brain work that went into the ideas! I used the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.socialfish.org/2016/11/you-have-more-content-than-you-realize/&#34;&gt;content pillars&lt;/a&gt; to come up with a plan. Every project group was given a public repository on GitHub to house their code and documentation. In a 2-day unconference with 70 people in 20 projects, how do people present their results?! We told everyone that they had just three minutes to present, and that the only presentation material they could use was their project README (the page of documentation in their code repository). No slides allowed! This kept their focus on great documentation for the project rather than an ephemeral set of pretty slides. Practically speaking, this meant that all presentations were accessible from a single laptop connected to the projector and that to access their presentation, a speaker had only to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropenscilabs.github.io/runconf17-projects/&#34;&gt;click on the link to their repo&lt;/a&gt;. Where did the essence of this great idea come from? From a pre-unconference chat of course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the week following the unconference, we used the projects’ README documentation to create a series of five posts released Monday through Friday, noting every one of the 20 projects with links to their code repositories. To get more in-depth stories about people and projects, I let participants know we were keen to host community-contributed blog posts and that accepted posts would be tweeted to rOpenSci’s &amp;gt;13,000 followers. Immediately after the unconference, we invited selected projects to contribute longer form narrative blog posts and posted these once a week. The series ended with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/blog/2017/08/08/unconfroadsnottaken&#34;&gt;Unconf 2017: The Roads Not Taken&lt;/a&gt;, about all the great ideas that were not yet pursued and inviting people to contribute to these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this content is tied together in &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/blog/2017/06/02/unconf2017&#34;&gt;one blog post to summarize&lt;/a&gt; the unconference and link to all staff- and community-contributed posts in the unconference projects series as well as to posts of warm personal and career-focussed reflections by some participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;6-care-about-other-people-s-success&#34;&gt;6. Care about other people’s success&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community managers do a lot of “emotional work”. In all of this, my #1 key to running a successful unconference is to genuinely and deeply care that participants arrive feeling ready to hit the ground running and leave feeling like they got what they wanted out of the experience. Ultimately, the success of our unconference is more about the human legacy – building people’s capacity as software users and developers, and the in-person relationships they develop within our online community – than it is about the projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve steered clear of ‘hackathons’ because they feel intimidating and the ‘bad’ kind of competitive. But, this….this was something totally different.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– rOpenSci unconf17 participant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/introducing-the-2017-community-engagement-fellows/&#34;&gt;AAAS Community Engagement Fellows Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://socialinsilico.wordpress.com/2014/11/07/all-together-now-event-formats-for-more-practical-sessions/&#34;&gt;All together now: Event formats for more practical sessions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Budd A, Dinkel H, Corpas M, Fuller JC, Rubinat L, Devos DP, et al. (2015) Ten Simple Rules for Organizing an Unconference. PLoS Comput Biol11(1): e1003905. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003905&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003905&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Governance, Engagement, and Resistance in the Open Science Movement: A Comparative Study</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/06/sholler-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/10/06/sholler-plan/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;A growing community of scientists from a variety of disciplines is moving the norms of scientific research toward open practices. Supporters of open science hope to increase the quality and efficiency of research by enabling the widespread sharing of datasets, research software source code, publications, and other processes and products of research. The speed at which the open science community seems to be growing mirrors the rapid development of technological capabilities, including robust open source scientific software, new services for data sharing and publication, and novel data science techniques for working with massive datasets. Organizations like rOpenSci harness such capabilities and deploy various combinations of these research tools, or what I refer to here as open science infrastructures, to facilitate open science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As studies of other digital infrastructures have pointed out, developing and deploying the technological capabilities that support innovative work within a community of practitioners constitutes just one part of making innovation happen. As quickly as the technical solutions to improving scientific research may be developing, a host of organizational and social issues are lagging behind and hampering the open science community’s ability to inscribe open practices in the culture of scientific research. Remedying organizational and social issues requires paying attention to open science infrastructures’ human components, such as designers, administrators, and users, as well as the policies, practices, and organizational structures that contribute to the smooth functioning of these systems.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These elements of infrastructure development have, in the past, proven to be equal to or more important than technical capabilities in determining the trajectory the infrastructure takes (e.g., whether it “succeeds” or “fails”).&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a postdoc with rOpenSci, I have begun a qualitative, ethnographic project to explore the organizational and social processes involved in making open science the norm in two disciplines: astronomy and ecology. I focus on these two disciplines to narrow, isolate, and compare the set of contextual factors (e.g., disciplinary histories, research norms, and the like) that might influence perceptions of open science. Specifically, I aim to answer the following research questions (RQ):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ1a: What are the primary motivations of scientists who actively engage with open science infrastructures?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ1b: What are the factors that influence resistance to open science among some scientists?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;RQ2: What strategies do open science infrastructure leaders use to encourage participation, govern contributions, and overcome resistance to open science infrastructure use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. To what extent do governance strategies balance standardization and flexibility, centralization and decentralization, and voluntary and mandatory contributions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. By what mechanisms are open science policies and practices enforced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c. What are the commonalities and differences in the rationale behind choices of governance strategies?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I describe how I am systematically investigating these questions in two parts. In Part 1, I am identifying the issues raised by scientists who engage with or resist the open science movement. In Part 2, I am studying the governance strategies open science leaders and decision-makers use to elicit engagement with open science infrastructures in these disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-1-engagement-with-and-resistance-to-open-science&#34;&gt;Part 1: Engagement with and Resistance to Open Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am firmly rooted in a research tradition which emphasizes that studying the uptake of a new technology or technological approach, no matter the type of work or profession, begins with capturing how the people charged with changing their activities respond to the change “on the ground.” In this vein, Part 1 of the study aims to lend empirical support or opposition to arguments for and against open science that are commonly found in opinion pieces, on social media, and in organizational mission statements. A holistic reading of such documents reveals several commonalities in the positions for and against open science. Supporters of open science often cite increased transparency, reproducibility, and collaboration as the overwhelming benefits of making scientific research processes and products openly available. Detractors highlight concerns over “scooping,” ownership, and the time costs of curating and publishing code and data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am seeking to verify and test these claims by interviewing and surveying astronomers and ecologists or, more broadly, earth and environmental scientists who fall on various parts of the open science engagement-to-resistance spectrum. I am conducting interviews using a semi-structured interview protocol&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; across all interviewees. I will then use a qualitative data analysis approach based on the grounded theory method&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to extract themes from the responses, focusing on the factors that promote engagement (e.g., making data available, spending time developing research software, or making publications openly accessible) or resistance (e.g., unwillingness to share code used in a study or protecting access to research data). Similar questions will be asked at scale via a survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with themes from the responses, I will clarify and refine the claims often made in the public sphere about the benefits and drawbacks of open science. I hope to develop this part of the study into actionable recommendations for promoting open science, governing contributions to open science repositories, and addressing the concerns of scientists who are hesitant about engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-2-focusing-on-governance&#34;&gt;Part 2: Focusing on Governance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with interviews and surveys of scientists on the ground, it is difficult to systematically trace and analyze the totality of social and political processes that support open science infrastructure development because the processes occur across geographic, disciplinary, and other boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as others have pointed out,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the organizational and social elements of digital infrastructure development often become visible and amenable to study through infrastructure governance. Governance refers to the combination of “executive and management roles, program oversight functions organized into structures, and policies that define management principles and decision making.”&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Effective governance provides projects with the direction and oversight necessary to achieve desired outcomes of infrastructure development while allowing room for creativity and innovation.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Studying a project’s governance surfaces the negotiation processes that occur among stakeholders—users, managers, organizations, policymakers, and the like—throughout the development process. Outcomes include agreements about the types of technologies used, standards defining the best practices for technology use, and other policies to ensure that a robust, sustainable infrastructure evolves.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the scientific research community’s increasing reliance on open science infrastructures, few studies compare different infrastructure governance strategies&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and even fewer develop new or revised strategies for governing infrastructure development and use.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The primary goal of this part of the project is to address this gap in our understanding of the governance strategies used to create, maintain, and grow open science infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am administering this part of the study by conducting in-depth, semi-structured interviews with leaders of various open science infrastructure projects supporting work in astronomy and ecology. I define “leaders” in this context as individuals or small groups of individuals who make decisions about the management of open science infrastructures and their component parts. This set of leaders includes founders and administrators of widely-used scientific software packages and collections of packages, of open data repositories, of open access publication and preprint services, and various combinations of open science tools. Furthermore, I intend to interview the leaders of organizations with which the open science community interacts—top publication editors, for example—to gauge how open science practices and processes are being governed outside of active open science organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will conduct qualitative coding as described above to develop themes from the responses of open science leaders. I will then ground these themes in the literature on digital infrastructure governance—which emphasizes gradual, decentralized, and voluntary development—and look for avenues to improve governance strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the interview and survey methods, I am actively observing and retaining primary documents from the ongoing discourse around open science in popular scientific communication publications (e.g., &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Science&lt;/i&gt;), conferences and meetings (e.g., OpenCon and discipline-specific hackweeks), and in the popular media/social media (e.g., &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt; and Twitter threads).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;preliminary-themes&#34;&gt;Preliminary Themes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I entered this project with a very basic understanding of how open science “works”—the technical and social mechanisms by which scientists make processes and outputs publicly available. In learning about the open science movement, in general and in particular instantiations, I’ve begun to see the intricacies involved in efforts to change scientific research and its modes of communication: research data publication, citation, and access; journal publication availability; and research software development and software citation standards. Within the community trying to sustain these changes are participants and leaders who are facing and tackling several important issues head-on. I list some of the most common engagement, resistance, and governance challenges appearing in interview and observation transcripts below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;participation-challenges&#34;&gt;Participation challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overcoming the fear of sharing code and data, specifically the fear of sharing “messy” code and the fear of being shamed for research errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defending the time and financial costs of participation in open science—particularly open source software development—to supervisors, collaborators, or tenure and promotion panels who are not engaged with open science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding time to make code and data usable for others (e.g., through good documentation or complete metadata) and, subsequently, finding a home where code and data can easily be searched and found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;governance-challenges&#34;&gt;Governance challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigating the issue of convincing researchers that software development and data publication/archiving “count” as research products, even though existing funding, publication, and tenure and promotion models may not yet value those contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing guidelines and processes for conducting peer review on research publication, software, and data contributions, especially the tensions involved in “open review.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deciding whose responsibility it is to enforce code and data publication standards or policies, both within open science organizations and in traditional outlets like academic journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The points raised in this post and the questions guiding my project might seem like discussions you’ve had too many times over coffee during a hackathon break or over beers after a conference session. If so, I’d love to hear from you, even if you are not an astronomer, an ecologist, or an active leader of an open science infrastructure (dsholler at berkeley dot edu). I am always looking for new ideas, both confirming and disconfirming, to refine my approach to this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- references --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Braa, J., Hanseth, O., Heywood, A., Mohammed, W., Shaw, V. 2007. Developing health information systems in developing countries: The flexible standards strategy. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 31(2), 381-402. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148796&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148796&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Tilson, D., Lyytinen, K., Sørensen, C. 2010 Digital infrastructures: The missing IS research agenda. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 21(4), 748-759. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1100.0318&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1100.0318&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Borgman, C. L. 2010. &lt;i&gt;Scholarship in the digital age: Information, infrastructure, and the Internet.&lt;/i&gt; MIT Press, Cambridge, MA. ISBN: 9780262250863
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Vaast, E., Walsham, G. 2009. Trans-situated learning: Supporting a network of practice with an information infrastructure. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 20(4), 547-564. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1080.0228&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1080.0228&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Spradley, J. P. (2016). &lt;i&gt;The ethnographic interview&lt;/i&gt;. Longegrove, IL: Waveland Press. ISBN: 0030444969
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Corbin, J., Strauss, A.,  1990. Grounded theory research: Procedures, canons, and evaluative criteria. &lt;i&gt;Qualitative Sociology&lt;/i&gt;, 13(1), 3-21. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00988593&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00988593&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;Barrett, M., Davidson, E., Prabhu, J., Vargo, S. L. 2015. Service innovation in the digital age: Key contributions and future directions. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 39(1) 135-154. DOI: 10.25300/MISQ/2015/39:1.03
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;Hanford, M. 2005. Defining program governance and structure. &lt;i&gt;IBM developerWorks&lt;/i&gt;. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/rational/library/apr05/hanford/&#34;&gt;https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/rational/library/apr05/hanford/&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;Star, S. L., Ruhleder, K. 1996. Steps toward an ecology of infrastructure: Design and access for large information spaces. &lt;i&gt;Information Systems Research&lt;/i&gt;, 7(1), 111-134. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.7.1.111&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.7.1.111&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;Edwards, P. N., Jackson, S. J., Bowker, G. C., Knobel, C. P. 2007. &lt;i&gt;Understanding infrastructure: Dynamics, tensions, and design. Final report for Workshop on History and Theory of Infrastructure: Lessons for New Scientific Cyberinfrastructures&lt;/i&gt;. NSF Report. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/49353&#34;&gt;https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/49353&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;Hanseth, O., Jacucci, E., Grisot, M., Aanestad, M. 2006. Reflexive standardization: Side effects and complexity in standard making. &lt;i&gt;MIS Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 30(1), 563-581. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148773&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/25148773&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Hanseth, O., &amp;amp; Lyytinen, K. (2010). Design theory for dynamic complexity in information infrastructures: the case of building internet. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Information Technology&lt;/i&gt;, 25(1), 1-19.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Value of #Welcome</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/07/18/value-of-welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/07/18/value-of-welcome/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-info&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;
I’m participating in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aaas.org/cefp/about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AAAS Community Engagement Fellows Program (CEFP)&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation. The inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/introducing-the-2017-community-engagement-fellows/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cohort of Fellows&lt;/a&gt; is made up of 17 community managers working in a wide range of scientific communities. This is cross-posted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/the-value-of-welcome/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trellis blog&lt;/a&gt; as part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/tag/fellows-blog-series&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; series of reflections&lt;/a&gt; that the CEFP Fellows are sharing.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my training as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/introducing-the-2017-community-engagement-fellows/&#34;&gt;AAAS Community Engagement Fellow&lt;/a&gt;, I hear repeatedly about the value of extending a personal welcome to your community members. This seems intuitive, but recently I put this to the test. Let me tell you about my experience creating and maintaining a #welcome channel in a community Slack group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;blimages&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.trelliscience.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/4344878104_e537b0248b_z.jpg&#34;&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/90371939@N00/4344878104&#34;&gt;&#34;Welcome&#34;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/90371939@N00/&#34;&gt;Nathan&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.0&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listen in on and occasionally participate in a Slack group for &lt;a href=&#34;http://rladies.org/&#34;&gt;R-Ladies&lt;/a&gt; community organizers (R-Ladies is a global organization with local meetup chapters around the world, for women who do/want to do programming in R). Their Slack is incredibly well-organized and has a #welcome channel where new joiners are invited to introduce themselves in a couple of sentences. The leaders regularly jump in to add a wave emoji and ask people to introduce themselves if they have not already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At rOpenSci, where I am the Community Manager, when people joined our 150+ person Slack group, they used to land in the #general channel where people ask and answer questions. Often, new people joining went unnoticed among the conversations. So recently I copied R-Ladies and created a #welcome channel in our Slack and made sure any new people got dropped in there, as well as in the #general channel. The channel purpose is set as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A place to welcome new people and for new people to introduce themselves. We welcome participation and civil conversations that adhere to our &lt;a href=&#34;http://unconf17.ropensci.org/coc&#34;&gt;code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pinged three new rOpenSci community members to join and introduce themselves, and in the #general channel said “Hey, come say hi to people over here at #welcome!”. One day later, we already had 33 people in #welcome. I spent that morning nurturing it, noting some people’s activities and contributions that they might not otherwise highlight themselves &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Chucheria&#34;&gt;Bea&lt;/a&gt; just did her first open peer software review for rOpenSci, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/metamattj&#34;&gt;Matt&lt;/a&gt; has been answering people’s questions about meta data, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/juliesquid&#34;&gt;Julie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ben_d_best&#34;&gt;Ben&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jafflerbach&#34;&gt;Jamie&lt;/a&gt; are co-authors on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-017-0160&#34;&gt;cool new paper&lt;/a&gt; about open data science tools. And I gave a shoutout to R-Ladies stating clearly that I copied their fantastic #welcome channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are introducing themselves, tagging with emoji and thanking “the community” saying things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“…I feel super lucky to be a part of the rOpenSci community, which has … had a great positive impact on my life!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I love rOpenSci for building this community and helping people like me become confident data scientists!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[I’m] hoping to contribute more to the group moving forward”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…thank you for having me part of this community!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such is the value of #welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
