<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Usgs on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/usgs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Usgs on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/usgs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting our USGS app</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/19/usgs-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/19/usgs-app/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;R has a reputation of not playing nice on the web. At rOpenSci, we write R pacakages to bring data from around the web into R on your local machine - so we mostly don&amp;rsquo;t do any dev for the web. However, the United States Geological Survey (USGS) recenty held &lt;a href=&#34;http://applifyingusgsdata.challenge.gov/submissions/14242-taxaviewer&#34;&gt;an app competition&lt;/a&gt; - it was a good opportunity to play with R on the web. We won best overall app as described in &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/blog/2013/04/22/usgs_app/&#34;&gt;an earlier post on this blog&lt;/a&gt;. Check out our app &lt;strong&gt;TaxaViewer&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://glimmer.rstudio.com/ropensci/usgs_app/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Last week we presented the app to the USGS - a video of the presentation will be coming soon. A screenshot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
{{ &amp;ldquo;assets/blog-images/usgsapp.png&amp;rdquo; | image_url }}
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we submitted the app we had static ggplot2 maps, but now the app has interactive maps that are a much better fit for a browser that isn&amp;rsquo;t restrained to static images. Ramnath Vaidyanathan helped us use &lt;a href=&#34;http://rcharts.github.io/&#34;&gt;rCharts&lt;/a&gt; to pass data from queries to the GBIF and BISON APIs to functions in rCharts to prepare the map page you see in the app. rCharts isn&amp;rsquo;t restricted to just maps - think interactive bar charts, scatter plots, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t originally have a tab for searching for mentions of taxonomic names in the literature - we added it in later (see the &lt;em&gt;Papers&lt;/em&gt; tab on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://glimmer.rstudio.com/ropensci/usgs_app/&#34;&gt;app&lt;/a&gt;), and people really liked it, suggesting that&amp;rsquo;s something we should explore more. How does it work? We take the list of taxonomic names input in the text box in the upper left, and query the &lt;a href=&#34;http://api.plos.org/&#34;&gt;PLOS search API&lt;/a&gt;, and return a table of papers listing the journal name and paper title. We provide a link to open an article from the search results in Macrodocs (thx &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/invisiblecomma&#34;&gt;@invisiblecomma&lt;/a&gt;!), like &lt;a href=&#34;http://macrodocs.org/?doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0017580&#34;&gt;this example&lt;/a&gt;. We chose PLOS as they have a relatively large set of articles, and they are all open access = immediate access to the text. Any interest in an app just for literature? Maybe litereature + metadata? And perhaps some text mining using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tm/index.html&#34;&gt;tm package&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think of the USGS app as a visual interface to show what can be do in R on the command line, and give the code to do it. See the code (&amp;lt;/&amp;gt;) buttons that drop down in this screenshot below. This is a compelling use case for Shiny apps - show people what they can do visually - then give them the code to do it on their own machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
{{ &amp;ldquo;assets/blog-images/codemodal.png&amp;rdquo; | image_url }}
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
