<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Funding on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/funding/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Funding on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/funding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing the rOpenSci Fellowships Program</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/07/06/ropensci-fellowships/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2017/07/06/ropensci-fellowships/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;rOpenSci&amp;rsquo;s mission is to promote a culture of open, transparent, and reproducible research across various research domains. Everything we do, from developing high-quality open-source software for data science and, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/onboarding#ropensci-onboarding&#34;&gt;software review&lt;/a&gt;, to building community through events like our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/commcalls/issues&#34;&gt;community calls&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://unconf17.ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;annual unconference&lt;/a&gt; are all geared toward lowering barriers to reproducible, open science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rOpenSci Fellowship presents a unique opportunity for researchers who are engaged in open source to have a bigger voice in their communities. These fellowships are designed to support individual researchers and collaborative efforts to help them do better science, build community around projects or best practices, or develop some tools as part of ongoing research that could impact one or more research domains. Two areas that are of particular interest to us are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/strong&gt;
The first type of fellowship we seek to support includes any activities (software development, best practices, guidelines) that promote reproducibility with one or more research communities. Funds from this fellowship can be used for activities such as finishing development of software, documentation or developing guidelines and best practices around methods and approaches. Your proposal will need to clearly identify how these funds will impact others in your research community and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working groups&lt;/strong&gt;
The second type of activity we seek to support is working groups, based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/system/files/HamptonParker_BioSci_2011.pdf&#34;&gt;a highly successful problem-solving model&lt;/a&gt; pioneered by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/&#34;&gt;National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis&lt;/a&gt;. You propose a critical challenge in the area of scientific open source and reproducibility, and a team of experts, to collaborate intensively for a week at a time. The knowledge and insight your team develops must be broadly relevant to the research community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first fellowship was awarded to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/blog/2016/12/12/ropensci-fellowship-zoon&#34;&gt;Dr. Nick Golding&lt;/a&gt; in suppport of a reproducibility project. Each fellowship will be in the range of $30,000 to $50,000.  We plan to award 2-3 fellowships (exact number to be determined by the size, scope, and quality of applications we receive) in 2017. We expect to have a similar call in 2018. All successful fellows will also receive additional travel support to participate in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/blog/2017/06/02/unconf2017&#34;&gt;annual unconference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fellowship-eligibility-and-criteria&#34;&gt;Fellowship eligibility and criteria&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fellows must be affiliated with a research institution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must have Principal Investigator (PI) status at your institution to receive funds from this fellowship. If you do not have PI status, or do not expect to have PI status by the time these funds are disbursed, you will need to collaborate with someone who can fulfill this role. For this stage of the application, you will only need to list your status and if necessary, the name of person who will serve as your PI. We will request a formal letter of support in a later round.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fellowship recipients must strive to spend all funds within a year of the start date. While we are able to accommodate extensions for exceptional circumstances, we strongly prefer to support projects that are scoped well enough to be completed within one year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funds can only be used to support personnel and travel. We do not allow purchase of equipment, or computing services. A detailed budget will be required in the final round.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funds cannot be used to organize conferences or hackathons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fellowship-selection-committee&#34;&gt;Fellowship selection committee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/about/#team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Karthik Ram&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Committee Chair
Karthik is a co-founder of rOpenSci and the project lead. Karthik is also a fellow at the Berkeley Institute for Data Science and the Berkeley Initiative in Global Change Biology at UC Berkeley. Prior to joining Berkeley, he earned his PhD in ecology &amp;amp; evolution from the University of California, Davis. Karthik&amp;rsquo;s interests are focused on reproducible research, especially as it applies to global change. Much of his recent work focuses on building tools and services around open data and growing diverse data science communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.stat.duke.edu/~mc301/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mine Cetinkaya-Rundel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Duke University
Mine is Associate Professor of the Practice at Duke University and a Professional Educator at RStudio. Her work focuses on innovation in statistics pedagogy, with an emphasis on computation, reproducible research, open-source education, and student-centered learning. She is the author of three open-source introductory statistics textbooks as part of the OpenIntro project and teaches the popular Statistics with R MOOC on Coursera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kenbenoit.net/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ken Benoit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, London School of Economics
Kenneth Benoit is Professor of Quantitative Social Research Methods at the London School of Economics and Political Science. He is active in data science and natural language processing and quantitative text analysis for social research. He is the creator of the quanteda, readtext, and spacyr R packages for text analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/ecoinfo#team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew Jones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis
Matt is the Director of Research and Informatics at the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis and has spent more than a decade developing various global data sharing infrastructure projects such as the KNB Repository and the DataONE federation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dicook.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Di Cook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,  Monash University
Di is Professor of Business Analytics at Monash University in Australia. Her expertise is in data visualisation, exploratory data analysis, and interactive graphics. She is an Ordinary Member of the R Foundation and a Fellow of the American Statistical Association.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;applying-for-the-fellowship&#34;&gt;Applying for the fellowship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, please submit a 3-page proposal that describes your goals, expected outcomes, a tentative timeline, collaborators, and a very high level budget (no more than a paragraph or two) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/fellowships&#34;&gt;ropensci.org/fellowships&lt;/a&gt;. As part of your submission form, you will also have to provide details about your affiliation, PI status, and the name of your PI (if you cannot serve in that role). For applicants that make the short list, we will request a detailed budget and may also ask for additional clarification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application deadline is September 1, 2017 (midnight PST).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the fellowship are welcome at fellowships@ropensci.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect a FAQ page shortly as we receive questions.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rOpenSci Announces $2.9M Award from the Helmsley Charitable Trust</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2015/11/19/helmsley-trust-funding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2015/11/19/helmsley-trust-funding/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;rOpenSci, whose mission is to develop and maintain sustainable software
tools that allow researchers to access, visualize, document, and publish
open data on the Web, is pleased to announce that it has been awarded a
grant of nearly $2.9 million over three years from &lt;a href=&#34;http://helmsleytrust.org/&#34;&gt;The Leona M. and
Harry B. Helmsley Charitable Trust&lt;/a&gt;. The
grant, which was awarded through the Trust’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://helmsleytrust.org/programs/health-biomedical-research-infrastructure&#34;&gt;Biomedical Research
Infrastructure Program&lt;/a&gt;, will be used to expand rOpenSci’s mission of developing tools and community around open data and reproducible research practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rOpenSci is a project at the University of California, Berkeley that
began a little over three years ago as a small collaboration among a few
researchers who intended to package data-retrieval scripts. The founders
wanted the data underlying their analysis to be open and easily
accessible to everyone. The project has since grown into a widely
recognized worldwide collaborative effort that plays an important role
in fostering open and transparent scientific practices across the
research community. rOpenSci supports an ecosystem of more than 50
software packages, engages scores of collaborators from nearly two dozen
countries, and has conducted dozens of workshops worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rOpenSci team has improved tools for researchers who consume open
data and work closely with scientists to help them develop research
software. In addition, the project has fostered a thriving community of
researchers who develop software through open peer review and
conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding from the Helmsley Charitable Trust will allow the rOpenSci team to develop new tools that support various pieces of the reproducible research workflow as the team continues to maintain the existing rOpenSci suite of software. The rOpenSci team is also planning a partnership with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://datacarpentry.org&#34;&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; (DC) project, a not-for-profit organization that runs two-day training workshops to help researchers develop basic data science skills. This partnership will allow DC to run rOpenSci-themed workshops (lessons taught with an emphasis on rOpenSci tools for data sharing, acquisition, retrieval, and visualization). Over the course of this partnership, the team hopes to develop a comprehensive corpus of openly licensed teaching material to be used at two-day workshops, as part of classroom curriculum, or for self-guided learning. These new training activities will provide the project with a comprehensive set of community resources, including lessons and tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To scale up efforts in all of these areas, rOpenSci will be expanding
its team over the coming months. New job postings, including those for a
community manager, software engineer, and postdoctoral fellow, among
various other short-term positions, will be posted on rOpenSci’s
website. Over the coming months, the rOpenSci team will also announce
details of a new fellowship program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embark on a new phase for the project, we would like thank our
community and contributors, without whom this effort would not succeed.
We also offer a special thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://weecology.org&#34;&gt;Ethan White&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://datacarpentry.org&#34;&gt;Tracy Teal&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://third-bit.com&#34;&gt;Greg
Wilson&lt;/a&gt; for the feedback, advice, and
encouragement they provided as we developed this proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The rOpenSci project&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;is a project based at UC&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://bids.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s
Institute for Data Science&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;and Berkeley Initiative for Global Change Biology with previous funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation. Founded in 2011, the project develops tools to support key parts of the data life cycle, from lowering barriers to access to validation and permanent archiving. A key part of rOpenSci’s mission is also to train the next generation of researchers as both consumers of data and developers of scientific software.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Leona M. and Harry B. Helmsley Charitable Trust&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;aspires to improve lives by supporting effective nonprofits in health, place-based initiatives, and education and human services. Since 2008, when the Trust began its active grantmaking, it has committed more than $1.5 billion for a wide range of charitable purposes. The Trust’s Biomedical Research Infrastructure Program seeks to lower barriers for biomedical discovery through the development of research tools, training and collaborative platforms that improve the quality and reproducibility of preclinical research. For more information, visit &lt;a href=&#34;http://helmsleytrust.org&#34;&gt;helmsleytrust.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New fiscal sponsorship agreement with NumFocus foundation</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2014/10/01/numfocus-partnership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2014/10/01/numfocus-partnership/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;I’m very pleased to announce that rOpenSci has signed a comprehensive &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiscal_sponsorship&#34;&gt;fiscal sponsorship agreement&lt;/a&gt; with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://numfocus.org/&#34;&gt;NumFocus foundation&lt;/a&gt;, a 501&amp;copy;3 nonprofit that supports R&amp;amp;D for open source scientific software projects. We are delighted to be in the company of esteemed projects such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipython.org/&#34;&gt;IPython&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://julialang.org/&#34;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; that share our goal of promoting reproducible research practices across many scientific communities and developing a rich ecosystem of tools for open scientific computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of our activities, from hackathons and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/blog/2014/08/11/ambassadors-program/&#34;&gt;ambassador program&lt;/a&gt; to salaries for our full-time personnel, are 100% grant supported at this time. While we will continue to pursue all possible federal and private funding to support future efforts, our continued success necessitates a diverse funding model. Given the current funding climate additional donations from individuals, institutions, and corporations are critical to help us remain sustainable and give us the ability to scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funds that we receive through NumFocus will go towards various community activities (hackathons, conferences, sprints), support for our community members to travel to meetings, and helping us grow our team. As more substantial funding become available, we hope to provide salary support both for short-term staff and additional full-time personnel to come on board. All of our plans for the future are visible in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci&#34; title=&#34;rOpenSci · GitHub&#34;&gt;Github repos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://discuss.ropensci.org&#34; title=&#34;rOpenSci · Discuss&#34;&gt;discussion forum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ropensci &amp;quot;rOpenSci (@rOpenSci&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; | Twitter&amp;rdquo;), and this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Boettiger, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uregina.ca/science/biology/people/faculty-research/simpson-gavin/index.html&#34; title=&#34;Gavin Simpson | Biology, University of Regina&#34;&gt;Gavin Simpson&lt;/a&gt;, and I make up the financial oversight committee for all funding that we receive through NumFocus. We are particularly indebted to &lt;a href=&#34;http://numfocus.org/foundation/staff.html&#34; title=&#34;NumFOCUS Foundation -&#34;&gt;Leah Silen&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://andy.terrel.us/&#34; title=&#34;Codematician&#34;&gt;Andy Terrel&lt;/a&gt; from NumFocus and &lt;a href=&#34;http://fperez.org/&#34; title=&#34;Welcome &amp;amp;mdash; Fernando Pérez&#34;&gt;Fernando Perez&lt;/a&gt; from IPython for helping us set up this agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to contribute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All contributions to rOpenSci from US organizations and individuals are tax deductible donations. If you would like to support our activities, we are now able to accept donations in a variety of forms including PayPal, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitpay.com/invoice?id=HvFM4eRTTscFKzuwK9Pqth&#34;&gt;BitCoin&lt;/a&gt;, or checks made out to &lt;strong&gt;NumFOCUS&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;i&gt;note &lt;b&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/b&gt; in the memo line&lt;/i&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NumFOCUS
P.O. Box 90596
Austin, TX 78709
USA
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34; target=&#34;_top&#34;&gt;
&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34;&gt;
&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;QVW5YFTJEFS62&#34;&gt;
&lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;first last&#34;&gt;&lt;form action=&#34;https://bitpay.com/checkout&#34; method=&#34;post&#34; &gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;action&#34; value=&#34;checkout&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;posData&#34; value=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;data&#34; value=&#34;RB/WxxHHgnPMjN0YyUijaAt3zS8ANaE0aoaNSiGxrBEZK3IrtDUEDF44QQU+nQVgofeuxCUMsWkjuBlAVXIXF1a4CI4+CfwrPFL4HOMB1BqTkeWVijGZiFVT2/O5fjc/34NIkVaftlLW8NHsS/m5p+5+5t8VGJ+OK/NOT9qz8d2pzMv5EcBUwQ8Q31sNvuZSzvwamDtT+51w2nNCVu6r+FRjdrErOPoI7yU4IViv+Numu55KoL3urtm4Id1zOHw6&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; src=&#34;https://bitpay.com/img/donate-md.png&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; alt=&#34;BitPay, the easy way to pay with bitcoins.&#34; &gt;
&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rOpenSci awarded $300k from the Sloan Foundation</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2014/06/10/new-sloan-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2014/06/10/new-sloan-award/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re delighted to announce that we have received additional funding from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sloan.org/&#34;&gt;Sloan Foundation&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/12/sloan/&#34;&gt;continue&lt;/a&gt; and expand our efforts from the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re grateful for the overwhelming support from the community, especially through engagement at various events we organized and attended this past year. Over the next year we plan to: &lt;strong&gt;advance not only the technical infrastructure for accessing, managing, and synthesizing large and heterogeneous data, but also the social infrastructure of research to facilitate collaboration and exchange of data, methods, and ideas so they can be easily reproduced and extended&lt;/strong&gt;. Over the next several months you can expect to see various tools that allow for seamless data interoperability, a comprehensive spatial and mapping toolkit, and a new suite of tools to support reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Sloan for continuing this relationship. Thanks especially to the Program Director &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/epistemographer&#34;&gt;Josh Greenberg&lt;/a&gt; for championing our vision for better science, the reviewers for critical feedback, and to everyone who wrote us a letter of support. We&amp;rsquo;re thrilled to bring on additional full-timers and work towards becoming a sustainable project.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What we hope to accomplish with the new funding</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/14/goals-for-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/14/goals-for-year/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;At rOpenSci&amp;rsquo;s virtual HQ we&amp;rsquo;re busy planning out several exciting projects for the coming year thanks to the generous &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/12/sloan/&#34;&gt;180k grant from Sloan&lt;/a&gt;. In the interest of maintaining transparency with our community here are additional details of what we hope to accomplish and how we&amp;rsquo;ll measure our successes. We have also posted a full copy of our proposal over at &lt;a href=&#34;http://figshare.com/articles/rOpenSci_Open_Tools_to_Facilitate_Data_Driven_Science_in_Ecology_and_Evolution/719786&#34;&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives-for-the-year&#34;&gt;Objectives for the year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Focus on identifying shortcomings, strengthening our core products, and working to link existing tools through interoperable data structures and visualization routines. To facilitate this process, we will convene two hackathons, one with the core development team and advisors and a second with a wider group of rOpenSci collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Build a general purpose toolkit that will allow researchers in any community to develop their own tool to access domain specific data. This toolkit will help researchers access data sources available via application programming interfaces (API) and other, less-structured data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) Conduct outreach and training workshops at universities and conferences. In addition to increasing awareness of our tools and growing our user base, we will also use this opportunity to assess challenges and barriers to data science in closely related fields. As part of this process, we will interact with scientists outside of Ecology and Evolution to identify disciplines that could immediately benefit from more data science tools and training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d) Explore long-term sustainability models for the project. This first year of funding will allow us to explore options, including strengthening the position of the organization to solicit similar funding from foundations and also pursue grants through National Science Foundation’s Office of CyberInfrastructure and related agencies while continuing to operate within the confines of academic institutions. We will also explore establishing a non-profit, either independently or in collaboration with a university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-we-ll-measure-our-success&#34;&gt;How we&amp;rsquo;ll measure our success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acquire at least 30K unique visitors annually to rOpenSci website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have at least five papers (published or in press) citing one or more of rOpenSci’s packages as a vital component of their methods sections (not including any work by the core development team)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage with researchers at ecology, biostatistics, and interdisciplinary meetings with surveys to track shifts in attitude towards open science, open data, and programmatic access through R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify potential future opportunities and ambassadors in other research disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://figshare.com/articles/rOpenSci_Open_Tools_to_Facilitate_Data_Driven_Science_in_Ecology_and_Evolution/719786&#34;&gt;full grant proposal&lt;/a&gt;. We welcome any comments and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rOpenSci awarded 180K from The Sloan Foundation</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/12/sloan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2013/06/12/sloan/</guid>
      <description>
        
        &lt;p&gt;Today we are pleased to announce that rOpenSci has been awarded a generous 180K grant from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sloan.org/&#34;&gt;Alfred P. Sloan foundation&lt;/a&gt;. This funding will allow us to develop a whole new suite of tools and provide scientists with general purpose toolkits to access various kinds of scientific data. We will also be traveling a whole bunch this year and running workshops at several conferences and universities. If you&amp;rsquo;d like us to speak to your research group, please &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/contact.html&#34;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll be at several events over the coming months including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/news/nceas-leads-hands-primer-ecoinformatics-ecological-society-americas-2013-conference&#34;&gt;The Ecological Society of America annual meeting&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://okcon.org/&#34;&gt;The Open knowledge conference&lt;/a&gt;, Science Online Climate, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.agu.org/meetings/&#34;&gt;American Geophysical Union&lt;/a&gt; and several others. Stay tuned for announcements on &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ropensci&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, our &lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://ropensci.org/feed.xml&#34;&gt;rss&lt;/a&gt;) and new mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
