<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researchsoftware on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</title>
    <link>https://ropensci.org/tags/researchsoftware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researchsoftware on rOpenSci - open tools for open science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ropensci.org/tags/researchsoftware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Software sustainability research with rOpenSci</title>
      <link>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/05/25/software-sustanability-ropensci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ropensci.org/blog/2016/05/25/software-sustanability-ropensci/</guid>
      <description>
        
        

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to announce that I’ve started a project with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org&#34;&gt;rOpenSci&lt;/a&gt;
under &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/blog/2015/11/19/helmsley-trust-funding/&#34;&gt;their recent award from the Helmsley Foundation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work with rOpenSci will focus on sustainability of the project itself.  Sustainability can be defined as having the
resources to do the necessary work to continue and grow rOpenSci.  This is one of the most difficult challenges for
rOpenSci and for many other research software projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rOpenSci has a very broad and very ambitious goal, as stated on their web site, &amp;ldquo;Transforming science through open data.&amp;rdquo;
In practice, the work being done by rOpenSci is &amp;ldquo;creating packages that allow access to data repositories through the
R statistical programming environment&amp;rdquo; with tools that “not only facilitate drawing data into an environment where it
can readily be manipulated, but also one in which those analyses and methods can be easily shared, replicated, and
extended by other researchers.”
An interesting question is how much rOpenSci will choose to move beyond R to meet its goal, which I would encourage as
much as possible.  I actually might rephrase the goal as &amp;ldquo;Transforming science through open data and open software&amp;rdquo;
better matching what is now happening in the project while not calling out R, since I would prefer to try to affect
the non-R science community as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sustainability-resources-work&#34;&gt;Sustainability = Resources &amp;gt; Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of sustainability models that have worked for other open source projects
to bring in the resources needed to do the work,
such as institutional support, diversified grants, membership fees, donations and gifts, fees for services, volunteers,
etc.  With the rOpenSci team, I will test elements of these models for rOpenSci.  As part of this, I will also work
with the rOpenSci leadership team to identify new funding opportunities for rOpenSci from public and private funding
organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will discuss and document how other projects have increased their scale of impact without an equivalent
increase in their staff, and how these models could work for rOpenSci.  I and the rOpenSci team will then test elements
of one or more of these activities.  I will also seek to find new partnership opportunities for rOpenSci with academic,
government, and private organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainability is a key challenge for many academic open source projects, as I saw when I was leading NSF&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=504817&#34;&gt;SI2 program&lt;/a&gt;.  One of the review criteria for proposals
to this program was to describe the proposed sustainability plan.  Few proposers gave fully convincing plans,
and the most common was probably to have a diverse set of funding sources.  Additionally, many projects
decided that they would leave sustainability until near the end of the project.  While we don&amp;rsquo;t know what
will lead to sustainability for academic open source software,
it seems clear that waiting to address it is not likely to make the effort
more successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can solve this for rOpenSci, or even just make progress and
provide guidance for other projects about what might work and what
probably won&amp;rsquo;t, this will be a significant contribution.
The &lt;a href=&#34;http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk/&#34;&gt;WSSSPE&lt;/a&gt; events will be a way to bring together
some of the academic open source community to understand how our lessons apply to other
projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;promoting-open-source&#34;&gt;Promoting Open Source&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of this work with rOpenSci, which overlaps some of my other work, involves ideas about how to develop the
overall scientific software community.
Working with the rOpenSci project and the wider scientific software community, I will examine incentives,
citation/credit models, and metrics, including understanding contributions of people in teams; funding models;
multi-disciplinary science; career paths for software developers and scientists who also develop some software;
software engineering; software communities and sociology; training and education; software dissemination, publication,
and peer review; catalogs, search, and review; portability; and reproducibility.  At least some of this will be done
under the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk/&#34;&gt;WSSSPE&lt;/a&gt; umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also work with rOpenSci to attempt to promote and encourage software
metrics. A number of projects, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/njsmith/sempervirens&#34;&gt;sempervirens&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://depsy.org&#34;&gt;Depsy&lt;/a&gt;, have begun to focus on particular parts of the problem space, but more general work and
tools are needed, in particular to impact those outside of just the R and python communities.  There’s also some
related work underway at NCSA and RENCI (that came out of WSSSPE3) to survey a set of developers on what impact
metrics they find useful, and I think the results of the survey will also help this overall community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-culture-around-open-source-needs-improvement&#34;&gt;The Culture around Open Source Needs Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to try to change our cultural understanding around the idea of open
source software.  The fact that open source software is commonly viewed as free software is a problem, since to many
people, free means of no value.  In particular, I believe we need to try to get to the point where companies that
make heavy use of open source software feel that they have an obligation to support either the software or its
developers in some way.  This is part of the larger sustainability discussion, since this is the way that open
source projects can gain more resources and reduce the amount of work that they have to do internally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts, comments, or suggestions are welcome. This is also cross-posted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://danielskatzblog.wordpress.com/2016/05/25/software-sustainability-research-with-ropensci/&#34;&gt;Dan&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
